<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>True religion makes the best loyalty discovered and recommended in a sermon, prepar'd for that Assembly which intended to meet at St. Michael's Cornhil, April 21, 1682, and afterwards preach'd at the New Church in Westminster, May 29, being the happy day of His Majesty's birth and return, and now published, at the earnest request of the gentlemen of that vestry / by Thomas Jekyll ...</title>
            <author>Jekyll, Thomas, 1646-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46730</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J539</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3602</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12892197</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12892197</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95130</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46730)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95130)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 716:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>True religion makes the best loyalty discovered and recommended in a sermon, prepar'd for that Assembly which intended to meet at St. Michael's Cornhil, April 21, 1682, and afterwards preach'd at the New Church in Westminster, May 29, being the happy day of His Majesty's birth and return, and now published, at the earnest request of the gentlemen of that vestry / by Thomas Jekyll ...</title>
                  <author>Jekyll, Thomas, 1646-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5-40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jonathan Robinson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 40.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 40.</note>
                  <note>First edition.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs XXIV, 21 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Loyalty --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95130:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>True Religion makes the beſt Loyalty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diſcovered and Recommended in a SERMON Prepar'd for that Aſſembly which intended to meet at St. <hi>Michael</hi>'s <hi>Cornhil, April</hi> 21. 1682.</p>
            <p>And afterwards Preach'd at the <hi>New Church</hi> in <hi>WESMINSTER, May</hi> 29. being the Happy Day of His Majeſty's BIRTH and RETURN.</p>
            <p>And now publiſh'd, at the earneſt Requeſt of the Gentlemen of that VESTRY,</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS JEKYLL,</hi> M.A and Preacher at the ſaid <hi>New Church</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed for <hi>Jonathan Robinſon,</hi> at the Golden Lion in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. MDCLXXXII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:95130:2"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:95130:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PROV. 24.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>My Son, fear thou the Lord, and the King; and meddle not with them that are given to change.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THo' <hi>Solomon</hi> was himſelf a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Prince, whoſe Honour and ſafety conſiſted as much in the Loyalty and Faithfulneſs of his Subjects and People, as ever any Kings did; yet theſe words are not ſpoken by him to ſerve a Turn, and to ſupport or enlarge his own particular Power and Greatneſs, but as a neceſſary Means and Rule to eſtabliſh that Peace and Tranquillity, in which the Happineſs and Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of any Nation or Kingdom doth conſiſt. Had we indeed none but Kings and Rulers to recommend this Duty to us, we might poſſibly ſuſpect it guilty of too much Partiality and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign; but we find it quite otherwiſe, for the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of it hath been in all Ages ſtill urged upon us, with as much Zeal and Faithfulneſs, even by thoſe who have been the moſt oppreſs'd by it, as ever it was by thoſe who have had the largeſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95130:3"/>ſhare or Intereſt in it. The greateſt Princes and Monarchs upon Earth cannot well deſire a larger Power and Dominion than what the Scriptures give them, and all good Men own and acknowledg to belong to them; nor can the wiſeſt Politicians and Stateſmen in the World, either invent or deſire more firm and ſolid, more ſtrong and certain, more cogent and convincing Arguments to Loyalty and Subjection, than what are given us by St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul.</hi> And it's very well known how much their Actions were agreeable to their Doctrines, ſince all thoſe Hardſhips and Preſſures which they laboured under, could never provoke them to make any Attempts whatſoever againſt the Government they were either born or liv'd under. It's true, there was a general Clamour rais'd againſt them, and the reſt of the Apoſtles, as Men of dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Spirits and Principles, Enemies to all the Civil Governments in the World, and therefore not to be endured amongſt Men; but we never find any ſuch thing prov'd upon them; bring them but to the Teſt, and the quite contrary ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears;
<note place="margin">Acts 24.</note> as it did by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> when ſo ſolemnly arraign'd for ſuch things before <hi>Felix</hi> the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and ſo fiercely charg'd with them by <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullus</hi> a flattering Orator of thoſe Times. And this was the conſtant Doctrine and Practice of the Primitive Chriſtians for above three hundred
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95130:3"/>Years together, making no manner of reſiſtance againſt their Tyrannical Perſecutors, tho' they wanted neither for Strength nor Numbers; as <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who liv'd a little before that Time, in his excellent and learned Apology for the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, makes it plainly appear; till the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> began to inſult over their Fellow Biſhops, and to affect a Tyrannical Supremacy in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves over the whole Chriſtian World; before which, tho' there might be ſome fierce Bicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings amongſt Chriſtians, yet no ſuch open and rebellious Practices againſt the Civil Government were ever allow'd of, as were afterwards too too commonly ſeen amongſt them: And if any ſuch things have been ever at any time acted ſince, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſpecious pretences of Conſcience and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, we know to whom we are beholden for the firſt Contrivance, and how far the Hand of <hi>Joab</hi> is in them ſtill. And indeed, what could be otherwiſe expected from ſuch beginnings, when Chriſtianity was turned into a ſecular<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and made to promote a Temporal Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and that but baſely gotten too; for the firſt that ever eſtabliſhed that Doctrine, was an Adulterous Aſſaſſine and Bloody Rebel, that murder'd his Maſter; and the firſt that made his Markets of it, wanted neither for Pride nor Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs to make the moſt of it. And from hence it is that we may date thoſe bold and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95130:4"/>daring Attempts, to Dethrone and Murder Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors and Kings, which the Hiſtories of the latter Ages of the Church have been, and are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> clogg'd and loaded with; for tho' it's true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this many little Attempts were made againſt the Sovereign Powers by Excommunications and Cenſures, yet this never grew ſo rampant and outragious as afterwards, when Pride and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> bore ſo great a ſway amongſt thoſe Eccleſiaſtical Uſurpers. And no wonder if they who had ſo fairly begun to caſt off all Religion, &amp; given themſelves up to Villany and Luſt, ſoon learn'd to caſt off all Allegiance too: He that can prove falſe to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and rebel daily againſt his God, can never be truly loyal to his Prince, nor a Cordial Friend to any Government; and therefore we ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways find the beſt Men make the beſt Subjects, none doing more real Honour and Service to the King, than they who truly <hi>love and fear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God;</hi> and therefore the one is ſtill made the Motive to enforce and encourage the other: <hi>My Son, fear thou the Lord, and the King; and meddle not with their that are given to change.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the handling of which words, I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour,</p>
            <p n="1">I. To explain the fence and meaning of them.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Conſider the Nature of the Duty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in them.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:95130:4"/>
            <p n="3">III. By way of Application, endeavour to enforce this Duty upon our Practice.</p>
            <p>1. For the meaning of the words, in which I ſhall ſhew in what is mean by the <hi>fear of God.</hi> 2. What by <hi>fearing the King</hi> 3. What by <hi>being given to change.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. What is meant by fearing God, <hi>Fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou the word.</hi> This is ſometimes put for the whole Buſineſs of Religion, and domain the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſubſtance of that Duty which we owe to God, the chief part of which conſiſts of eight Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of him, becauſe where ſuch are, every other Duty will certainly follow. He that ſets God always before his Eyes, can never do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs, and the before the <hi>Pſalmist</hi> makes the want of this, the cauſe of all other Miſchiefs and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions in the World, <hi>The Wicked,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 10.4.</note> (ſaith he) <hi>through the pride of his Countenance, will not ſeek after God; God is not in all his thoughts:</hi> And then followeth, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſ.</hi> 7, 8, 9. <hi>His Mouth is full of Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, Deceit, and Fraud, under his Tongue, is Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief and Vanity. He ſitteth in the lurking places of the Villages; in the ſecret places doth he murder the Innocent. He lieth in wait ſecretly as a Lion in his Den, he lieth. in wait to catch the Poor;</hi> and tho' he cannot but ſometimes think of theſe things with remorſe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, yet then he flyeth unto his old Refuge, that either <hi>God doth not ſee,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 13.</note> or will
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95130:5"/>forget, and ſo never Require it.</hi> For no ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Man can commit a deliberate Act of Sin, that is fully perſuaded and convinced that God ſeeth and knoweth what he doth, and will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly call him to an account for it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the firſt thing that wicked Men do, is to baniſh this Principle from their Minds, for as long as there are any impreſſions of it there, the remembrance of their own Actions muſt needs be very uneaſy to them; and therefore hence it is, that the Scriptures, both of the Old and New Teſtament, lay every where ſo much ſtreſs upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and not only make it the Motive to, but the Sum and Subſtance alſo of all true Religion: and this it doth not only in general Terms, when it ſpeaks of God's immediate Worſhip and Service, but when it deſcends to the particular Duties which we owe unto our Neighbour alſo; they are often expreſſed by the ſame Phraſe. Thus, for the Duty of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and great Men. Saith <hi>David</hi> in his dying words,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 23.3.</note> 
               <hi>He that ruleth over Men, muſt be just, ruling in the Fear of God;</hi> that is, as becomes one who is not only in the preſence, but in the place of God;
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 19.7.</note> with whom <hi>there is no Iniquity, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Perſons, nor taking of Bribes.</hi> And ſo for any others that are in any other inferiour de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Power;
<note place="margin">Levit. 25.17, 42, 43.</note> 
               <hi>Ye ſhall not oppreſs one another<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſaith <hi>Moſes, but thou ſhalt fear thy God. Nay, if thy
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95130:5"/>Brother be ſold unto thee for a Bondman, thou ſhalt not rule over him with Rigour, but ſhall fear thy God; i.e.</hi> ſhalt uſe him with that merciful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard which God requires, and is well-pleaſed with. And thus the Duty of Subjects towards their Magiſtrates is expreſſed in words to the ſame effect, when we are required not only <hi>to be ſubject for Wrath, but alſo for Conſcience-ſake;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.5.</note> and what is that, but in the Fear of God; and therefore <hi>whoever reſiſts the Power,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 2.</note> reſiſts the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God;</hi> and what is that, but to caſt off the Fear of God! And thus alſo our Duty towards one another, in all Affairs and Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſes whatſoever is expreſſed;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.11, 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>Come ye Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>hearken unto me, and I will teach you the Fear of the Lord:</hi> and what is that? <hi>keep thy Foot from Evil, and thy Lips from ſpeaking Guile. Depart from Evil, and do good; ſeek Peace and purſue it.</hi> Thus ſaith the wiſe Man, <hi>The Fear of the Lord is to hate Evil.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 8.13.</note> So that by the <hi>Fear of the Lord,</hi> we are here to underſtand the ſincere and hearty Profeſſion and Practice of True Religion; the doing the Duties of our particular Places, with an honeſt Mind, and as we will anſwer it to God. And this I have been the longer upon, becauſe it helps us both to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand and practiſe the following Duty of <hi>Fearing the King;</hi> which comes now to be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined and explained.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:95130:6"/>
            <p n="2">2. What is meant by <hi>fearing the King.</hi> And here we may eaſily underſtand the meaning of this Duty, by comparing it with the former; for according to the particular Nature and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of it, it hath the ſame ſignification with that; for as the one teacheth us what is True Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſo the other teacheth us what is True Loyalty; for as the one conſiſts in a rational ſincere and dutiful Affection and Zeal for God and his Intereſt, ſo doth the other for the King and his: they only differ in Degree, as the one is ſubordinate and muſt give place unto the other, tho' to none beſides: for as we are to be obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for Conſcience-ſake, in the Fear of God, ſo we are to be ſo according to the Will of God; for if any thing is required that is contrary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto,
<note place="margin">Acts 5.29.</note> we all know that <hi>God is to be obeyed rather than Man.</hi> Nor doth this at all derogate from the Duty of the Text, but rather confirm and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it; for if Kings are to be feared and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, as they are God's Vicegerents, then whatever doth diſhonour God, reflects alſo upon them; and therefore thoſe that are truly zealous to preſerve the one, do beſt ſecure and uphold the other; nor doth this in the leaſt eclipſe their Power and Dominion, but leaves them to the full exerciſe of it, ſince it never alloweth us to rebel againſt it, but rather to yield to it, and to ſuffer by it; which when we chearfully and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95130:6"/>do, we ſhew we are more tender of the King's Honour and Safety, than we are of our own; which is certainly the trueſt Principle of Loyalty, and the beſt demonſtration of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty of our Intentions in the practice of this Duty: for tho' the Government may by this means be ſometimes croſſed of its Will, yet it's never in danger as to its ſafety.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What is meant by being <hi>given to change?</hi> The word in the Original, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſignifies <hi>Changers,</hi> and ſo it's rendred in the Margent; and it is ſometimes taken in a good fence, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in a bad.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is ſometimes taken in a good ſenſe, for thoſe neceſſary Changes and Alterations that are made in things that are amiſs, which it is every Man's Duty, in the place wherein he is ſet, by all honeſt and juſt Ways and Means to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour; but this cannot be <hi>Solomon</hi>'s meaning here. Therefore,</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is taken ſometimes, and here more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, in a bad fence, for thoſe that rather endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to diſturb thoſe things that are well; and therefore it is properly tranſlated, by being <hi>given to change;</hi> that is, Perſons of unſetled Minds, govern'd by no Principles, either of Religion or Honeſty; whoſe Profit or Luſt is the only thing they are guided by, and which no Government can have any certain ſecurity againſt; fickle
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95130:7"/>and unconſtant Men, that always turn with the Times; meer Weathercocks both in Religion and Government, and therefore true neither to God nor the King; whoſe Religion is only Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of State, and whoſe Loyalty is either Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt or Humour, and (to ſpeak according to the preſent Diſtemper of our Times) Proteſtants to day, Papiſts to morrow, any thing the next, and yet all this while nothing at all. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore well doth the wiſe Man caution us againſt ſuch as theſe, as the moſt dangerous Company we can keep; for they that have no honeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the Intereſt of True Religion, can have none to their King and Country; he that every day makes bold with Almighty God, and ſets him at defiance in the manifeſt breach of his Laws, for the ſake of his Pleaſure, or of his Profit, can never give his Prince any tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſecurity, that he will not ſerve him ſo upon the like occaſion: and this is the reaſon why Princes are many times ſo unfortunate in the choice of their Miniſters, becauſe it is an hard matter to find a great Politician to be as good a Man, one who always makes the Laws of God and his Country the conſtant meaſure of his Actions, let what will happen to him; which if they did but truly fear God, they would certainly be and do. And this leads me to the ſecond thing propounded, which is, to conſider,</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:95130:7"/>
            <p n="2">II. The Nature of this Duty: The meaning of which is, I ſuppoſe by this time, pretty well underſtood; and therefore that which I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour next, ſhall be to ſhow,</p>
            <p>That True Religion, called here <hi>the Fear of God,</hi> is the beſt ſecurity of true Loyalty; and that thoſe Perſons who fear God moſt, will ſerve the King beſt: And this I ſhall do in three ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. True Religion fixeth Men to certain Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, which any Government may ſafely rely upon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It cuts off all occaſions of Rebellion and Diſloyalty.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It urgeth ſtronger Motives, and layeth greater Obligations upon us to be truly Loyal, than any thing in the World can beſides.</p>
            <p n="1">1. True Religion fixeth Men to certain Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, which any Government may ſafely rely upon. The Actions of Men either are or ſhould be ſtill governed by ſome Principle or other, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Truth or Falſhood of which they are always either good or bad. Now for thoſe Perſons that have no Principles at all, it's only by chance if ever they are good, and therefore no Government can ſafely confide in them. Now True Religion layeth down ſuch Principles as are to be truſted, ſuch as ſecure and maintain the Civil Rights of all Men; and take care, not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95130:8"/>only that <hi>God,</hi> but that <hi>Ceſar</hi> alſo may have his utmoſt Due; which are ſuch as theſe. (1.) That we muſt by no means do wrong, tho' we have Power enough, and can do it without Danger or Diſcovery; nay, we muſt rather take Wrong than do it. (2.) That we muſt not revenge our ſelves when it is done unto us. (3.) That we muſt always ſpeak and act according to the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Verdict of Truth. (4.) That Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Princes are not to be reſiſted by force of Arms, much leſs to be Depos'd and Murder'd. Nay, (5.) That True Religion it ſelf is not to be propagated or eſtabliſh'd by Violence and Blood.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) True Religion teacheth us, That we muſt by no means do Wrong, tho' we have Power e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and can do it without Danger or Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, nay, we muſt rather take Wrong than do it; True Religion is very tender of the Rights of all Men; and tho' it lays none under the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of being wrong'd, yet it reſtrains all from the doing of it, in any kind whatſoever: it makes an Hedg about every Man's Liberty and Property; fenceth and encloſeth him in from Violence and Rapine; ſecures him againſt open Force and ſecret Fraud, that he ſhall neither be overpowred by the one, nor undermined by the other, but continue ſafe under its Protection, from all the mercileſs Attempts of the <hi>Sons of Violence,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:95130:8"/>and from all the treacherous and falſe Accuſations of the <hi>Sons of Belial;</hi> it never makes the faireſt Opportunity a ſufficient Warrant to the doing of Miſchief, nor the cloſeſt Privacy an encouragement thereto; but by ſhewing us the All-ſeeing Eye of God, and the certainty of his Vengeance, makes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Man to become his <hi>Brother's Keeper;</hi> and therefore whoever offers injuriouſly to invade us in any kind, tho' under never ſuch ſpecious Pretences, and guarded by never ſo great a Power, is a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Enemy, and a notorious diſturber of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Peace of Mankind, and hazards the Peace and Tranquillity of any Government whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) True Religion allows us not to revenge our ſelves when we are wrong'd. Had it made no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for our Reparation and Satisfaction in ſuch Caſes, we might poſſibly think hardly of it; but ſince it hath made better than any we can think of beſides, we can never certainly do better, than to have recourſe thereunto upon all ſuch occaſions; and as long as we do ſo, the Honour and Safety of the Government is as well provided for as our own, and both of them better than any other way: It is an unreaſonable and a dangerous thing, for any Man to be his own Carver in ſuch Matters; for if a Man is not to be a Judg in his own Caſe, he is not certainly to be the Executioner of his own Wrath: and, bleſſed be God, there is no need of either, for God hath provided ſuch Ways as are fitter for both;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95130:9"/>he hath conſider'd us as we are Men united into Society, and therefore neceſſarily under Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and hath therefore placed the Power of avenging us, in ſuch hands as are beſt able and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt to do it; and to them we not only lawfully may, but we muſt too always reſort for it: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle calls Magiſtrates,
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> 
               <hi>the Miniſters of God; Revengers to execute Wrath upon all that do evil:</hi> and, as if this were the chief thing, he tells us, that otherwiſe they do but <hi>bear the Sword in vain.</hi> Nay, ſo careful is True Religion to give all poſſible ſecurity to the Civil Government, againſt this dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Evil, that it forbids us all private Revenge, tho' the Magiſtrate himſelf either neglect or refuſe to right us;
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.19.</note> 
               <hi>Dearly Beloved, avenge not your ſelves, but rather give place unto Wrath:</hi> Submit with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence &amp; chearfulneſs to the preſent neceſſity of your Condition, for you are not left deſtitute of Help and Relief; the Great God will take your Cauſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his own Hand, and will do you right; <hi>Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is mine, ſaith the Lord, I will repay:</hi> And he that can thus ſtop his own Mouth, tie up his own Hands, and peaceably wait God's Leiſure, tho' it be till the Day of Judgment before he be righted, can never be a bad Subject.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) True Religion teacheth us always to ſpeak and act, according to the Evidence and Verdict of Truth. As Peace is the great Bleſſing of Society, ſo Truth is the great Conſervator of it; take away
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95130:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>that, and we are ſtrip'd naked of our beſt Defence, either againſt the Malice and Violence of Men, or the Wrath and Juſtice of God: And therefore this hath he en always required, as one of the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, both of Religion and Government, <hi>That we ſhould, every Man, ſpeak the Truth unto his Neighbour,</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Zechariah</hi> expreſſeth it, <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.16, 17. <hi>Speak ye every Man the Truth to his Neighbour; execute the Judgment of Truth and Peace in your Gates, and let none of you imagine Evil in your heart againſt his Neighbour, and love no falſe Oath.</hi> For when once it comes to this, that we cannot believe and truſt one another, how can we tell how to diſcern between right and wrong and know either who or what is good or bad? And therefore the want of this, was that which the Prophets, all as it were, with one conſent, complain of; not only as a very ill thing in it ſelf, but as the certain Forerunner of approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ruin: for beſides the Juſtice of God, which it provokes more than any thing elſe, it is in it ſelf a Scourge and a Plague, which no Remedy can be provided againſt; it's like that fretting Leproſy under the Law, which nothing but the pulling down of the Houſe could cure; it's the bane of all Society, a dangerous Civil War, even in the midſt of Peace, ſince it ſets <hi>every Man's Hand againſt his Fellow,</hi> and yet no Enemy appears. Now True Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion provides a Remedy againſt this, by preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the God of Truth unto us, as more concern'd
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95130:10"/>for it, than for any thing elſe, becauſe he himſelf is always made a Party to it: for every Lye we tell, is a bold and impudent denial of his Being, whoſe very Eſſence is Truth; and every falſe Oath we take, is to 'vouch his Authority againſt the plaineſt Declarations of his Nature and Will; and therefore it is better for us to ceaſe to be Men, than to ceaſe to be true, for no Government can need our Perſons ſo much as our Truth and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) True Religion teacheth us, that Sovereign Princes are not to be reſiſted by force of Arms, much leſs to be Depos'd and Murder'd; you ſee how careful it is to ſecure the Perſons and Rights of private Men, that none may be wrong'd and injur'd in either; and if ſo, much more doth it take care of the Prerogatives of Princes. And there's nothing more plain and evident than this, even from the Doctrine and Practice of our Saviour and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and of all good Men in all Ages, affixing a Sacredneſs to their Perſons, equal to the Greatneſs of their Power: What can be more plain and full, than the Apoſtle's excellent Diſcourſe to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. and his charge to <hi>Titus</hi> to preach the ſame Doctrine afterwards? <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1. ſo far is True Religion from giving the leaſt countenance to Diſobedience and Rebellion. And that this proceeds not from weakneſs and want of Power, is evident enough; for our Saviour had a greater Power at
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95130:10"/>his command, than all the Powers of the Earth; and the ſame might have been as eaſily communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to his Church, had it been any ways eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to it. Nor did there, even at that time, want either for Opportunity or Provocation to reſiſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> had it been at all conſiſtent with it; for the Magiſtrates that were then, were as barbarouſly tyrannical and cruel as ever were; nay, they had uſurp'd their Power but a little before, and were then ſo odious, by the ſavage exerciſe of it, that there was indeed a very fair Opportunity offered thereby to ſhake off that heavy Yoke; for the <hi>Romans</hi> were weary of, and groan'd under the Oppreſſions of their inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and bloody Emperors: and the Jews were always forward enough to ſhake off a Forreign Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction; and there wanted not a conſiderable Party, even amongſt the Chriſtians, to run up <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> to a very great and formidable height; and yet, even then, the Apoſtles, all with one conſent, preach'd Obedience and Subjection to the Civil Powers, as being an <hi>Ordinance of God;</hi> upon which ſcore Religion it ſelf obligeth them to have always a very great veneration for it. Nay,</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) True Religion teacheth, that even its own Intereſt is not to be propagated and eſtabliſhed by Violence and Blood. There is nothing certainly dearer to good Men than their Conſciences, and there's nothing that they deſire more than the free Exerciſe and Enjoyment of them; and therefore
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95130:11"/>there is nothing ſo apt to provoke them, as reſtraints therein, becauſe nothing comes ſo near to them: the Arguments are at firſt ſight ſo plauſible and fair, the Cauſe it ſelf ſo honeſt and good, and the Succeſs ſo inviting, that it requires a more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary reſolution of Mind to forbear from Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; and certainly nothing but the Power of that Religion it ſelf, which is ſo dear to them, can do it: and therefore to prevent ſuch things, it preſents it ſelf to them as a mild and good-natur'd Thing, whoſe greateſt Force lies in its Sweetneſs, whoſe Arms are Convincing Reaſon, and Almighty Truth; and therefore <hi>the Weapons of whoſe Warfare are not Carnal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.4.</note> but ſuitable to the Enemies it fights with, which are Spiritual: It wages no War againſt Men's Perſons, but againſt their Luſts; <hi>captivates their Minds,</hi> and not their Bodies; beats down only their towring <hi>Imaginations,</hi> and not their other Caſtles and Forts: And of what uſe now are Swords and Guns for ſuch Service? What do they ſignify to the Reaſon of Men's Minds? They may be ſtrong, but they are very abſurd Arguments to rational Creatures; they may compel to a complyance, but they'l never prevail to a Conviction; for no Man can judg of any thing in the World, otherwiſe than his Reaſon and Underſtanding directs him. A Man may ſpeak and act contrary to his Judgment, (as God knows too too many of us do) but he can never think otherwiſe if he would never ſo
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95130:11"/>fain. A Man that ſees the Sunſhine at Noon-Day, may ſay, it is Midnight, and grope about as if it were ſo, but it's impoſſible for him to think ſo. A Papiſt may ſay, That the Bread in the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is tranſubſtantiated and made real Fleſh; but whilſt he ſees, and feels, and taſts all the Qualities and Properties of Bread; it's as impoſſible for him to think it ſo, as it is for his Prieſt to make it ſo; and therefore he hath need of a very luſty Faith in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to make it out. A Man may will and deſire a thing that's contrary to his Reaſon, but he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not change his Opinion about the nature of it, till his Reaſon and Judgment are fully ſatisfied in it. Beſides, True Religion preſents it ſelf to our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections as an amiable and lovely Thing, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns our real Good and Welfare: now that which raiſeth Wars and Commotions in the World, is both frightful and deſtructive, and begets Hatred and Deteſtation. How can we believe that Man deſires God's Glory, and our Good, that with an implacable Fury and Malice, (which is the true Image of the Devil) is ſtill doing us all the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief he can? Fire and Faggot, Blood and Slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, are ſtrange ways of making Love by, and wholly unknown to Chriſtianity, till the Romiſh Incendiaries firſt invented them. The Primitive Chriſtians knew not the way of firing Men's Houſes to root out their Hereſies, of plundring their Goods to convince their Conſciences, of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95130:12"/>tormenting their Bodies to beget Faith in their Souls, nor of abſolving Subjects from their Allegiance to their Princes, and thereby raiſing Rebellions and Wars, for their own Intereſt and Advantage, no nor for their own Safety and Preſervation; they were ſtill taught to commit God's and their own Cauſe to him who was beſt able to protect and defend both, and to keep themſelves always with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the bounds of Modeſty and Meekneſs, and by no Oppreſſions or Provocations whatſoever, to take up Arms againſt a Lawful Authority; by which diſpoſition and temper, it gives certainly the greateſt ſecurity that any Government can deſire. But yet it goes farther ſtill. For,</p>
            <p n="2">2. It cuts off all occaſions of Rebellion and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty; it not only lops the Tree, but it digs it up by the Roots, fights with the Small as well as the Great, as truly knowing what great and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Revolutions have proceeded from very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and contemptible Beginnings: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<list>
                  <item>(1.) It makes us diligent and induſtrious in our particular Callings.</item>
                  <item>(2.) It makes us ſerious and conſiderate.</item>
                  <item>(3.) It makes us loving and charitable, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur'd and kind.</item>
                  <item>(4.) It makes us temperate and ſober. Nay,</item>
                  <item>(5.) It ties even our Tongues and our Thoughts to their good behaviour.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:95130:12"/>
            <p n="1">(1.) It makes us diligent and induſtrious in our particular Callings; for Idleneſs is a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous thing to the State, and therefore to be time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly provided againſt. They that have nothing to do, are ready for any miſchief, and for this as ſoon as any other; and when any Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity offers it ſelf, they are ſome of the firſt that run in to do hurt; for as they are the ſowers of Diſcord in Times of Peace, ſo they are the moſt turbulent and miſchievous in Times of War. Now True Religion provides a Remedy againſt this, by obliging all Men to ſome honeſt <hi>Calling</hi> or other, and to a daily and induſtrious dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence therein, and that perhaps with as great ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity as any one Temporal Concern in the World. <hi>This we command you,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 3.10.14.</note> 
               <hi>that if any would not work, neither ſhould he eat;</hi> nay, he was to be baniſhed the ſociety of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. <hi>Note that Man,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and have no company or fellowſhip with him, that he may be aſhamed;</hi> a thing, which it were to be heartily wiſhed were a little more ſeriouſly conſider'd of in this Age, in which ſo many neglect their Callings, and live too like thoſe <hi>Strangers at Athens,</hi> who ſpent their time, for the moſt part, in hearing or telling of News; an Evil certainly of very dangerous conſequence, not only to ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons themſelves, who are thus fond of it, but alſo to the publick Peace and Tranquillity of the Nation.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:95130:13"/>
            <p n="2">(2.) It makes us ſerious and conſiderate, and by conſequence conſtant and fix'd to our Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. Now Rebellion is always the effect of Raſhneſs and a giddy Mind, and proceeds from a vain and fooliſh deſire of Change: And this the words of the Text have a particular reſpect unto, and provide againſt, by making the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> which is always one and the ſame, the conſtant Rule and Meaſure of all our Actions and Deſigns.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) It makes us loving and charitable, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur'd and kind; a temper as directly contrary to all Sedition and Diſloyalty as can be; for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion is always an ill-natur'd thing, proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from Envy and Diſcontent, fomented by Hatred and Malice, and brought out into Act by Rage and Fury. Now True Religion allays Men's natural Heats, cures the Diſtempers of their Minds, charms their moſt head-ſtrong and unruly Paſſions; and not only reſtrains Violence and Wrath, but converts it into Love and Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; it unites us together in the moſt indiſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Bonds of Peace and Amity, and is ſo far from ſuffering us to <hi>Devour and Deſtroy,</hi> that it obligeth us to Preſerve, yea, even <hi>to die for one another:</hi> and to prevent all Miſtakes, it expreſly commands us to <hi>love our Enemies.</hi> So far hath it gone, and ſo much hath it done for the publick Intereſt of Society, and to ſecure the Peace and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95130:13"/>Tranquillity of it, and by conſequence to ſecure all Civil Governments, from any dangerous and rebellious Attempts and Practices.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) It makes us Temperate and Sober. And without this no Government can always be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and ſafe; for what ſtreſs can any wiſe Man lay upon Whoring and Drinking? Who can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide in ſuch Perſons who are ſo ſeldom their own Maſters? But admit that ſuch Perſons may be Men of Honeſty and Courage, yet who can expect the Bleſſing and Protection of Almighty God (without which there can be no true Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) amidſt ſuch Actions? If our Loyalty muſt be meaſur'd by the multiplicity of our Oaths, by the largeneſs of our Healths, and the number of our Whores, God help us. No, my Beloved, theſe are the things that diſpirit our Minds, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken our Hands, and deprive us of our beſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and are enough to ſpoil the beſt Cauſe in the World. I could inſtance in ſeveral Princes and States, who have receiv'd more hurt by the Debaucheries and Luxury of their Friends, than by the Malice or Strength of their Enemies, but that the thing is too plain and obvious to need any Example; and therefore Religion teacheth us to maſter our Luſts, that ſo we may at all times govern our Paſſions, and be always diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to Quietneſs and Peace.</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) It ties even our Tongues and our
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95130:14"/>Thoughts to their good behaviour: and there is very good reaſon it ſhould, for tho' the Tongue be but <hi>a little Member,</hi> yet it's oftentimes <hi>a very unruly one,</hi> and when let looſe, doth always a great deal of miſchief, and therefore is by no means to be left at Liberty; and therefore hence it comes to paſs, that Religion and Loyalty are both expreſſed by the ſame Phraſe, and ought both to be of the ſame Nature and Quality, <hi>i. e.</hi> hearty and ſincere. And therefore how ſeverely are they condemned by the Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">Jud. 8.</note> who <hi>deſpiſe Dominion, and ſpeak Evil of Dignities:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore well ſays the wiſe Man,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 10.20.</note> 
               <hi>Curſe not the King, no not in thy Thought, for the Bird of the Air ſhall carry the Voice, and that which hath Wings ſhall tell the Matter.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> indeed once, and that upon an extraordinary Provocation, betray'd too much of the heat of his natural Temper, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting ſeverely upon the High-Prieſt, for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding him to be ſmitten unjuſtly; but he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently checks himſelf for it, and acknowledges his Error before them all, and tells them, that it proceeded from Raſhneſs and Paſſion, and not from Religion or Deſign;
<note place="margin">Acts 23.5.</note> 
               <hi>I wiſt not, Brethren, that it was the High-Prieſt;</hi> I conſider'd not what I ſaid, nor to whom I ſpake; <hi>For it is written, Thou ſhalt not ſpeak evil of the Ruler of thy People:</hi> And therefore certainly, from ſo great an Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, founded upon ſo good an Authority, we
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95130:14"/>cannot but ſee the reaſonableneſs and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of this Duty, let the uſage we meet withal from them be what it will. Religion obliges us to ſuffer; and certainly Railing and Reviling are but ill Preparatives for it, and ſhew but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of that good Spirit which we pretend unto: And this brings me to the third and laſt thing, whereby True Loyalty is ſo much promoted by Religion; and that is, in that</p>
            <p n="3">3. It urges ſtronger Motives, and lays greater Obligations upon us to be truly Loyal, than any thing in the World can beſides: It propounds to us the Fear and Dread of the great God, the everlaſting Good and Welfare of our Souls, and the Concerns of Eternity, than which certainly nothing can be more great and prevalent upon us. Other Arguments from the ſweet and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Effects of Peace, from the Fury and Spoils of War, and the Hazards which we run in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging therein, can never be ſo ſtrong and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, but that great Provocations, ambitious Hopes, and greedy Deſires, may overcome them; but now the aſſurance that God is concern'd in the Protection and Defence of Sovereign Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, is beyond all; and therefore ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Ye muſt needs be ſubject,</hi> (it's no indifferent, but a neceſſary thing) <hi>and that not only for Wrath,
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.5.</note> but alſo for Conſcience ſake,</hi> in reſpect of the Laws of God, as well as of Man: And therefore if
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95130:15"/>we ſhould, either by force or cunning eſcape the one, yet we are ſtill in danger of the other; now there's no Man whatſoever kept ſo certainly within the Bounds of his Duty and Obedience, as he that ſets God always before his Eyes. This Conſideration alone kept <hi>David</hi> from killing <hi>Saul,</hi> under ſo many tempting Circumſtances, as I think never Man beſides had the like.
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 26.9.</note> 
               <hi>Who can ſtretch forth his hand againſt the Lord's Anointed, and be guiltleſs?</hi> And how far this Guilt extends it ſelf, is plainly told us by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> when he ſaith, That <hi>they which reſiſt,
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.2.</note> ſhall receive to themſelves Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation;</hi> that is, are liable to the Wrath and Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of God, as well as the Penalty of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Laws. And indeed, what are the ſevereſt Laws where this is wanting? What do all other Teſts ſignify? What are the faireſt Promiſes, the deepeſt Proteſtations, and the moſt ſolemn Oaths without this? Where this is not, nothing can bind us; ſo where this is, nothing can abſolve us. And this brings me to the third and laſt Thing propounded in the handling of theſe words; which is,</p>
            <p n="3">III. By way of Application, to enforce this Duty upon our Practice.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How ought we to bleſs God for ſuch excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Means for our Protection and ſafety. The Kindneſs he hath ſhewed to us, and the Care he
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95130:15"/>hath taken of us in all Ages, hath been exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great; he hath made us, as far as wholſome and good Laws, as far as a wiſe and excellent conſtitution of Government can, as happy a People as are under the Sun: And that nothing may be wanting to make us for ever ſo, he hath crown'd it all, with that ineſtimable Bleſſing of his moſt Divine and Sacred Truth, whereby all the reſt are both defended and enlarged. Time was, that this was a Stranger to us, and beſides the Light of Nature, (and that too was greatly obſcured) we had no farther knowledg of it, than what the Intereſt and Humour of a few in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent and luxurious Prieſts would allow of; and then neither Princes nor People knew what was their own, how far to command, nor how far to obey. Kings muſt ask leave to be crown'd, yea, and give ſufficient ſecurity for their Good-Behaviour, before they could obtain it; and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects muſt be Loyal, no farther than was conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with the Will of their Ghoſtly Father, and ſo every Man's Life and Fortune, yea, his Body and his Soul too, muſt be at their Mercy: But, bleſſed be God, it is otherwiſe now, for <hi>we have a more ſure Word of Prophecy, to which we do well if we take heed:</hi> And God grant we may, our Duty and Intereſt is founded upon a more certain Thing; our Safety and Welfare more ſecurely provided for, whilſt our Religion obligeth us
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95130:16"/>to be truly Loyal, and our Loyalty to be truly Religious; for he that is not truly Loyal, is no true <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> nor can he that is not a true <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> be truly Loyal: Our Religion and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are now ſo twiſted together, that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be falſe to the one, but we muſt betray the other: We can attempt nothing againſt the Government in any kind, but we forfeit all Title to that excellent Religion which we profeſs. A Rebellious <hi>Proteſtant</hi> is as great a contradiction as a Loyal <hi>Papiſt;</hi> for tho' one that calls himſelf a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> may be a Rebel, and one that calls himſelf a <hi>Papist</hi> may be Loyal; yet, according to the Principles of each Religion, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the particular Conſtitutions of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government, they can neither of them be as they pretend. And therefore,</p>
            <p n="2">2. How ought we to deteſt and abhor all ſuch Principles and Practices, as corrupt and overthrow ſuch an excellent Thing! Religion and Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, are and ought to be inſeparable Twins, and whoever offers to debauch and divide them, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves neither the Name of a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> nor the Priviledg of a Subject. To this we owe all the Faction and Sedition, the Treaſon and Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that have ſo ſtain'd and diſhonour'd the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſtianity. The truth of it is, we owe the firſt beginnings of theſe things under the Goſpel, to the Pride and Luxury of the Church
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:95130:16"/>of <hi>Rome,</hi> they taught ſome of the firſt Leſſons of Diſloyalty and Rebellion, tho' they have met with too many apt Scholars amongſt thoſe that call themſelves by a better Name; but let them pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend what they will, and ſtrive to alter the Name never ſo much, yet as long as they retain the thing, it is all one. We may call our ſelves <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> as much and as long as we pleaſe, but we are never the more ſo for that; for if we carry on any Seditious &amp; Treaſonable Deſigns under that plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Name, we forfeit our Title to it, and are <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or worſe (if it be poſſible) all the while, for the Primitive Chriſtians never thought of ſuch a thing; nay, ſo far were they from it, that there was more danger of the other extream of complying outwardly to avoid perſecution, with every thing which the Civil Government requir'd, tho' never ſo Idolatrous and Wicked; which gave the Apoſtles occaſion ſo fairly to ſtate the Queſtion between Subjection and Chriſtian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, both in relation to their Enemies and their Friends, to allay the Fears and Jealouſies of the one, and to rectify the Miſtakes of the other, in which they take the middle and ſafeſt way, of fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or ſuffering, rather than reſiſting: for as the <hi>Gnoſtick</hi> Compliance was to be deteſted as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy the plainneſs and ſimplicity of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; ſo all forcible Reſiſtance was to be avoided too, as directly contrary to the Innocence and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95130:17"/>Meekneſs of it. And therefore whoever they are that take upon them to do any ſuch thing, let their pretences be never ſo fair and plauſible, I am ſure <hi>they have not ſo learned Chriſt;</hi> not that the Chriſtian Religion deprives any Man of the liberty of a juſt Defence againſt any of the Sons of Violence; but then it muſt be only by ſuch ways as true Religion, and the particular Laws of his Country do allow of. Thus we have St. <hi>Paul</hi> twice pleading the Liberty and Priviledges of his Birth, to preſerve him from the Malice and Rage of his Enemies; once he inſiſts upon his being a <hi>Roman,</hi> to prevent his being ſcourged; and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time,
<note place="margin">Acts 22.25. &amp; 25.10, 11.</note> as ſuch, <hi>appeals unto Caeſar</hi> from the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh <hi>Sanhedrim.</hi> And thus doubtleſs may any Man flie to the known Laws of his Country, for his own fafety and preſervation; but to go beyond theſe, is dangerous and deſtructive; as is alſo the perverting the Deſign and Intention of them, and argueth as little fear of God, as it doth of Loyalty to the King, and good Affection to the Government we live under, which hath provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo excellently for our Defence and Security: for tho' we may pretend a very great veneration for the King and his Government; yet if we uſe his Name and Authority to undermine or overthrow the Fundamentals of it in any kind, we ſet the King againſt himſelf, as well as his Subjects; we leſſen his Power, by dividing his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95130:17"/>Intereſt; we ſtain his Honour, by making him give the lie to ſo many gracious Declarations of his Will, to make the known Laws of the Land the only Rule and meaſure of his Actions; and we let in Popery with all its miſchievous Effects and Conſequences, by the very ſame means we profeſs to keep it out: For every thing that brings Confuſion and Diſorder amongſt us, either by Force or Fraud, by open Rebellion, and an ill-gotten Power, or by a treacherous management of what we come more honeſtly by, is as meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious a piece of Service to that bloody Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as any we can do it, ſince it haſtens that which it moſt deſires and delights in, to wit, our own Ruin and Deſtruction. Which now that we may prevent, in the third and laſt place,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let us reſolve to perſevere in the practice of this Duty, whatever befal us. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the <hi>Fear of God;</hi> a Duty, or rather a Fundamental Principle, ſo eſſential to us, that we muſt ceaſe to be Men, before we can be void of it; ſo univerſally uſeful, that we muſt reſolve to become our own Enemies, before we can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline it; ſo rivited into that Religion which we profeſs, that we muſt fly in the face of our own Conſciences whenever we act againſt it; and yet, alas! a Duty ſo much neglected and deſpiſed in this Atheiſtical Heaven-daring, and God-dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Age wherein we live, as if it were a part of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:95130:18"/>our Religion to bid defiance unto God, and all that is good. And yet if it were indeed a part of it, I am apt to think it would not be ſo much in faſhion as it is; for we ſeem to glory in nothing more, than in running counter to every thing which ſome Men place Religion in, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering whether the thing be really ſo or no; As if, becauſe we have been ſometimes abus'd by Hypocriſy and Pretences, we muſt neceſſarily throw off that which we know to be ſincere and true. And that which makes it more to be lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is the ſanction that is put upon this untoward Humour, by making it a note of our Loyalty to the King, and our good Affection to the Church; as if drinking his Health, till we loſe our own, were a greater piece of Service to him than pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for his Life and Safety, ſubmitting to his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or chearfully offering up our Lives and Fortunes to the defence and ſupport of it; as if no conformity to the Church, tho' never ſo exact and canonical, no means to perſwade others to the like, tho' never ſo ſucceſsful, could make a Man ſo true a Son of it, as drinking the confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all that diſſent from it, and Damming and Hectoring every thing that is not of the ſame furious and violent temper with our ſelves. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, my Beloved, theſe things are as far from our Duty and Religion, as they are from our Peace and Safety; and therefore the allowing
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:95130:18"/>them ſo conſiderable a ſhare therein, muſt needs be very dangerous and deſtructive. Which that we may prevent or avoid, let us have recourſe unto thoſe things which the Spirit of God, who beſt underſtands the nature of it, hath wiſely, and with great plainneſs and ſimplicity placed True Religion in, even as <hi>Solomon</hi> here expreſſeth it, in the true <hi>Fear of God:</hi> which is very well explain'd by St. <hi>James,</hi> who calls it not only a <hi>pure and undefiled</hi> thing, but tells us too, That it is <hi>peaceable, gentle, and eaſy to be entreated,
<note place="margin">James 3.17.</note> full of Mercy and good Fruits, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, without partiality,</hi> as it's very fitly tranſlated, as it were on purpoſe to fit the Humour of our Times, or as it is in the Margent too, very properly rendred, <hi>without wrangling,</hi> and <hi>without hypocriſie</hi> and deceit; all which if we would but rightly and ſeriouſly conſider, we ſhould certainly avoid thoſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Evils which threaten us, both from abroad and at home. And therefore well doth the wiſe Man make it the foundation of True Loyalty, ſince it's not only ſupported by it, but it will prove deceitful, and vaniſh into Air and Nothing without it: for thoſe Men are always moſt <hi>given to change,</hi> the Principles of whoſe Religion are moſt fickle and inconſtant, and always adapted to Times and Occaſions, or elſe who have none at all to fix them to any certain Meaſures that may be confided in; but now the true <hi>Fear of God</hi> is a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:95130:19"/>fix'd and certain Thing, a ſure Guide to us, and a conſtant and powerful Security to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we live under; and diſpoſeth us every way for the practice of the other Duty of the Text, which is the only thing that now remains to be exhorted to. Therefore,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us be always loyal and true to the King and his Government. You ſee how much the Principles of that Religion which we profeſs do oblige us to it, and methinks there needs no other Argument or Motive to enforce it, and yet it may not be amiſs a little further to explain it; for as Religion in general is an ambiguous Term, and oftentimes made uſe of only to ſerve a Turn, and therefore applied then to all thoſe things that are proper for it; ſo is Loyalty too: And the King's Honour and Intereſt may be pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when both of them are, it may be, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, and betrayed. True Loyalty therefore conſiſts in a cordial Veneration for the King's Perſon as Sacred, and in a dutiful Submiſſion to his Laws and Government at all times: Not that every Man who breaks any of the Laws, is <hi>ipſo facto</hi> an Enemy to the Government, for then there would be no true Friends to it in the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<note place="margin">Jam. 3.2.</note> ſince, as St. <hi>James</hi> ſays in another caſe, <hi>In ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things we offend all.</hi> But then do we become Enemies to it, when we undermine or oppoſe thoſe Laws upon which the Government doth
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:95130:19"/>ſubſiſt, and which it is maintained and ſupported by, let them be never ſo uneaſy to us; which if they ſhould at any time be, and grind either up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Eſtates or Conſciences, we muſt not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently flie in the Face of that Authority which God hath ſet over us, and by Force of Arms en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to relieve our ſelves, but muſt with all cheerfulneſs ſubmit, even to the ſpoiling of our Goods, and the loſs of our Lives, till God ſhall find out a way for our Deliverance, and fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and crown our Patience. And tho' this be an hard Leſſon, yet it's a good one, and ſuch as the Primitive Chriſtians overcame their Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors by, and the Engliſh Martyrs founded that happy Reformation of Religion amongſt us upon; and ſuch as if we throughly learn, will provide the beſt for us againſt all Accidents whatſoever: But I truſt in God we ſhall never have any ſuch great occaſion for it, but that he will ſtill go on to protect and defend the Sacred Perſon of the King, that he may outlive even the treacherous Hopes and Expectations, as well as the undeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and implacable malice of his Enemies, who promiſe themſelves any Benefit or Advantage by his Death, and therefore wiſh and long for it, that he may be always a <hi>Nurſing Father</hi> unto this our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> a powerful Defender of that Faith, which as it enriches his preſent Crown, ſo it will entitle him to a better, that his Government may
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:95130:20"/>be for many and many Years the Glory and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of theſe Nations, as his Perſon hath been hitherto the Darling of God's Providence; which as it is the avowed Deſign of this Meeting to bleſs God for, ſo let it be the Buſineſs of our Lives to contribute all we can unto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And thus I have given you a Sermon, which was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed intended for another Occaſion; which becauſe I have been ſo ſeverely reflected upon for what I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took therein, I was reſolv'd to take this Opportunity to ſubmit it unto your Judgment, that ſo you may ſee, that the Perſon whom you have ſo unanimpuſly deſir'd and receiv'd for your Miniſter, is not a Man of thoſe dangerous Anti-monarchical Principles as ſome Men would endeavour to make the World believe; and if now you are but ſatisfied therein, I ſhall have the leſs reaſon to care whether any Body elſe be or no.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>In Page 15 line 21, read <hi>Principles.</hi> P. 19, l. 4. read <hi>been</hi> for <hi>he.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>POpery a great Myſtery of Iniquity, proved in a Sermon on 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.7. recommended in ſuch ſecure Proteſtants that will not believe there is a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Plot, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Righteouſneſs and Peace the beſt Means to prevent Ruin: Recommended in a Sermon preached at <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> Chappel, <hi>(Sept.</hi> 25. 1681.) before the Lord-Mayor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By the ſame Author. Both ſold by <hi>Jonathan Robinſon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
